Stephen E. Malawista papers
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Stephen E. Malawista papers
1957-2013
Ms Coll 46
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
82
Stephen E. Malawista, M.D, was a member of the Department of Internal Medicine and Chair of the Section of Rheumatology at Yale. His research focused on the mechanisms of inflammation relevant to rheumatology. He was best known as the co-discoverer of Lyme disease. His papers include correspondence, section annual reports, correspondence and drafts on papers submitted for publication, grants and contracts, popular material on Lyme disease, presentations, published papers, and research notes.
Malawista, Stephen E., 1934-2013
Biographical / Historical
Stephen Evan Malawista, professor of medicine at Yale, was born in New York City and graduated from Harvard College (1954) and the College of Physicians and Surgeons, Columbia University (1958). He completed his residency training at Yale. After a brief stint in the Public Health Service, he was invited back to Yale in 1966, where he became chief of Rheumatology in the Department of Internal Medicine in 1967. As chief for 21 years, he built up the section to a major center for rheumatology. Malawista was known for his creativity in the laboratory, his observational skills as a clinician, and his wit as a colleague. His research focused on inflammation, especially neutrophils, and he made many important contributions. He developed the first screen for the prenatal diagnosis of chronic granulomatous disease. But Malawista will be especially remembered as the co-discoverer in 1975 with Allen C. Steele, of Lyme disease. In addition to his previous areas of research, Malawista continued to investigate Lyme disease through the remainder of his career. He and his colleagues researched the causal mechanisms, diagnosis, etiology, and the treatment of Lyme disease, and the prevention of Lyme disease by a vaccine. All Malawista's sabbaticals were spent in Paris collaborating with various French colleagues. Malawista received several major awards, among them the Gold Medal of the American College of Rheumatology, the Ciba-Geigy/International League Against Rheumatism Prize with Allen Steere, and the degree of Docteur Honoris Causa from the Universite de Paris.
Scope and Contents
The papers include correspondence with individuals and organizations; administrative reports of the Section of Rheumatology; Yale committee minutes and correspondence; grants and contracts whether funded or not; manuscripts of papers, both published and unpublished, including correspondence with editors, reviews, and subsequent resubmissions to the same or other journals; popular and scholarly materials collected by Malawista on Lyme disease; presentations and travels to conferences; articles/reprints; protocols; and laboratory notebooks. Restricted materials containing patient information include Malawista's correspondence with patients, clinical research, clinical trials, and most research notebooks.
Conditions Governing Access
Most of the papers are open for research, but portions of the collection are restricted because they contain patient data. Consult the Librarian for Medical History.
Arrangement
Organized into 12 series: 1. General. 2. Correspondence. 3. Yale University: Administration, Teaching, Medical Practice, Sabbaticals. 4. Submission of manuscripts for publication. 5. Grant and contract proposals. 6. Lyme disease files, Part 1 (open). 7. Lyme disease files, Part 2 (restricted). 8. Lyme Vaccine Study (restricted). 9. Talks and Travel ("T/T"). 10. Published articles (reprints). 11. Research materials. 12. Oversize.
Arthritis; Borrelia burgdorferi; Chemotaxis; Cytology; Colchicine; Gout; Leucocytes; Lyme disease -- Connecticut; Lyme disease -- Diagnosis; Lyme disease -- Popular works; Lyme disease -- Prevention; Lyme disease -- Treatment; Melanocytes; Microtubules; Neutrophils; Phagocytes; Rheumatism; Correspondence; Photographs; Reprints; Rheumatologists -- Connecticut; Lyme disease -- Immunological aspects; Notebooks; Slides; Videocassettes; Chronic granulomatous disease; Barthold, Stephen W.; Beeson, Paul B. (Paul Bruce), 1908-2006; Bensch, Klaus G.; Bessis, Marcel, 1917-; Bodel, Phyllis; Chevance, Anne de Boisfleury; Cooney, Leo M.; Craft, Joseph E.; Curnutte, John T.; Duff, Gordon W.; Dyett, Deborah Elizabeth; Evans, Janine; Feinstein, Alvan R., 1925-2001; Fikrig, Erol; Flavell, R. A. (Richard A.); Gifford, Robert H.; Hardin, John A.; Kantor, Fred S.; Lerner, Aaron Bunsen; McCarty, Daniel J., 1928-; Montgomery, Ruth; Naccache, Paul H.; Persing, David H.; Rahn, Daniel W. (Daniel Wallace), 1950-; Satō, Hidemi, 1926-; Schoen, Robert T.; Seegmiller, J. E.; Serhan, Charles N.; Smallwood, Joan Irene; Steere, Allen C.; Blaricom, Gretchen Van; Van Damme, Jo; Weiss, Mary C.; Weissmann, Gerald; American College of Rheumatology; American Rheumatism Association; Arthritis Foundation; Arthritis Foundation. Connecticut Chapter; Association of American Physicians; Connaught Laboratories; G.D. Searle & Co; Gaylord Hospital (Wallingford, Conn.); International League against Rheumatism; Interurban Clinical Club; National Institutes of Health (U.S.); New Haven Foundation; Veterans Administration Hospital Medical Center (West Haven, Conn.); Yale-New Haven Hospital; Yale University. Department of Internal Medicine. Section of Rheumatology; Creasey, William A.; Thier, Samuel O., 1937-; Austen, K. Frank (Karl Frank)
- General, Series I
  - Curriculum Vitae, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Also attached to finding aid in electronic form.
  - Curriculum Vitae, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lists of publications, reviews, and abstracts, ca. 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Transcripts from Harvard College and Columbia University College of Physicians and Surgeons, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Also includes certification for additional courses Malawista took elsewhere.
  - U.S. Selective Service form, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Malawista served in the U.S. Public Health Service from July 1, 1960 to June 30, 1962. The form is a "Current Information Questionnaire."
  - Application for the International Geigy Rheumatism Prize, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Stephen E. Malawista, Allen C. Steere, and John A. Hardin applied as a group for the prize in 1980 based on their research on Lyme disease. The prize was awarded by the International League Against Rheumatism (ILAR). Malawista received a rejection letter for the application in 1981.
  - CIBA-GEIGY ILAR Rheumatology Prize, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Allen C. Steere and Stephen E. Malawista were jointly awarded this prize in 1986. Folder contains a brief note from the New Haven Register and large format photographs taken at the award ceremony.
  - Nomination for the Lee C. Howley, Sr. Prize for Arthritis Research, 1994-1997 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Malawista tried several times to receive this award from the Arthritis Foundation. The folder contains correspondence, letters of recommendation, and information on Malawista's accomplishments.
  - Nominations of Malawista for an award by Gerald Weissman, 1998; circa 2003 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Weissman discusses the achievements in Lyme disease research of Malawista versus Allen Steere and Willy Burgdorfer. The particular award is not mentioned.
  - Doctor Honoris Causa, Universite Rene Descartes, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Letter in French from Charles-Joel Menkes, March 14, 1998, drafts in French of Malawista's presentation on Lyme disease, and photocopies of the illustrations.
  - Honorary Degree photographs (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Malawista in an academic robe, and photo of Malawista and Tobe Ann Malawista, his wife. These probably relate to the Paris degree.
  - Stephen E. Malawista Symposium and "Festival", 2004 April 22-23 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    This event commemorating the work of Malawista took place on April 22-23, 2004. There was a dinner in the evening, and a symposium the next day, followed by a tour of the art museum. The folder contains the program for "Neutrophils and Inflammation: A symposium in Honor of Stephen E. Malawista, MD" held at Yale on April 23, 2004, and lists of the numerous people invited to attend the various events. There is a poster for the symposium in Box 82.
  - Application for the Eloi Collery prize of the Academie Nationale de Medecine, 2004 January 22 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Columbia University, College of Physicians and Surgeons, Gold Medal, 2006, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Letter to Dr. Sheldon C. Silverstein, Columbia, requesting a nomination for the Gold Medal, and a one-page biography. Malawista was awarded the Alumni Gold Medal in 2006.
  - Election to the Institute of Medicine, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Text of nomination sponsored by Samuel C. Silverstein, Columbia University, and Samuel O. Thier, Harvard University. Malawista was elected in 2007.
  - Solicitations for Malawista to be a candidate for a position, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Information on Malawista for various directories (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photographs of Stephen E. Malawista (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Additional photographs of Malawista and others (Box 1, Folder 20)
    A group of snapshots are from the "Pasteur Party." There are also a photograph and slide from "Showboat, Lake Placid," 1969, and paper copies of photographs with Janine Evans and Linda Bockenstedt, with Ruth Montgomery, with Rheumatology Clinic Fellows, and with lab manager Xiaomei Wang.
  - Miscellany on Stephen Malawista (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Newspaper articles on Tobe Anne Miller (Malawista), 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Tobe Anne Miller was a singer and actress who married Stephen Malawista in 1969.
  - Memorial service at Battell Chapel and obituaries, 2013-2014 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Malawista died on September 18, 2013. A memorial service was held at Battell Chapel at Yale University on October 23, 2013.
  - Biographical information for professional biographical dictionaries, 1971-1990 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - S. E. Malawista, Calendar, "Monthly Minders", 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Four ringed calendar notebooks for 1969, 1970, 1971, and 1972.
  - S. E. Malawista, Copies of calendar pages, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Copies of small format pages.
  - S. E. Malawista, "Month at a Glance", 1973 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Ringed calendar notebook.
- Correspondence, Series II
  - Individuals, A-N, Subseries 1
    - Abramson, Steven B, 1985-2000 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Amor, Bernard, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Ananyeva, Lydia P., 1989-1994 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Anderson, David, 1982-1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Åsbrink, Eva, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Askenase, Phillip W., 1984-1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Atkins, Elisha, 1975-1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Austen, K.F., 1981-1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - A, Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Badon, Stanley, 1993-1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Bainton, Dorothy Ford, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Barber, Fred Lee, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Beeson, Paul, 1980-1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Bensch, Klaus, 1968-1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Bennett, Claude J., 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Berliner, Robert, 1977-1983 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Bessis, Marcel, 1981-1993 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Binder, Henry, 1983-1988 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Bockenstedt, Linda, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Bray, Dennis, 1987-1990 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Burrow, Gerard, 1989-1997 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - B, Miscellaneous 1/2 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - B, Miscellaneous 2/2 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Cadman, Edwin, 1987-1993 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Calabresi, Paul, 1972-1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Calabro, John J., 1970-1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Chang, Yi-Han, 1968-1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Chevance, Anne, 1981-1986 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      General
      See also folders in Research Correspondence.
    - Chevance, Anne, 1989-2010 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Clancy, Robert, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Cline, Martin J., 1967-1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Cohen, Lawrence, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Cook, Phyllis, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Creasey, William A., 1969 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Crede, William, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Cronstein, Bruce N., 1989-1993 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Curnutte, John T, 1986-1992 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - C, Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Dinarello, Charles, 1986-2004 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Di Giovine, Francesco S., 1986-1990 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Dodd, Christopher J. (Senator), 1986 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Donaldson, Robert M, Jr., Vice-Chairman, Department of Internal Medicine, Yale, 1982-1987 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Duff, Gordon, 1983-1988 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Duff, Gordon, 1989-1997 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Dwyer, John M (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - D, Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Ehrlich, George E., 1969-1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Ephrussi, Boris, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - E, Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Feinstein, Alvin R., 1979-1990 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Finkelstein, James D., 1974-1986 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Friedheim, Ernst, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Fujiwara, Keigi, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - F, Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Gee, J. Bernard L., 1971-1983 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Genel, Myron (CURE), 1993 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Giacondino, David, Administration, 1974-1984 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Gillespie, Elizabeth, 1975, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Godman, Gabriel G., 1964-1985, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Goldenberg, Don L., 1982, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Goldfinger, Stephen E., 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Goldstein, Ira, 1975, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Gresham, Glen E, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Grokoest, Albert (includes obituary), 1971, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - G, Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Harris, Edward D, 1970-1987 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Harvath, Liana, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Hastie, Dr. Robin, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Hollingsworth, J. William ("Bill"), 1966-1985 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Holmes, Edward W., 1975 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Holmes-Grey, Beulah, 1967-1970 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Houck, John C., 1971 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Huang, Ada, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Hueber, Brigitte (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - H, Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Illouz, Gabriel, 1980-1982 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Ingelfinger, Franz J., 1976 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Inoué, Shinya (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Isaacs, Stephen T. (HRI Research), 1990 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - I, Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Jensen, Pamela, 1974-1981 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - J, Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Kafina, Martin, 198-2004 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Kaplan, Herbert, 1988-1992 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Kaplow, Leonard, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Katona, Gabor, 1972-1982 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Kaufman, William, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Kelley, William, 1975-1982 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Klinenberg, James, 1971-1985 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Kroc, Robert, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - K, Miscellaneous 1/2 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - K, Miscellaneous 2/2 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Lederberg. Joshua, 1981-1983 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Leonard, Edward J, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Lequesne, Michel, 1991-1993 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Levin, Jack, 1973-1991 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Levine, Philip, 1964-1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Lockshin, Michael, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Medical education survey
    - L, Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Malawista, Lawrence (father), 1963-1966 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Mandell, Gerald, 1972-1988 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - McCarty, Daniel J., 1976-1986 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - McDuffie, Frederic, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - McEwen, Currier, 1982-1984 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Melmon, Kenneth, 1978-1985 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Menkes, Charles-Joel, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Merigan, Thomas C. (Stanford), 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Moleski, Ronald J, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Moller, Halvor, 1984-1998 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Moore, Irwin, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Moore, Patrick, 1988-1991 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Moraes, Denzil, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Morgan, James, 1987-1990 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Mosby, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Myers, Frederick, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - M, Miscellaeous 1/2 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - M, Miscellaneous 2/2 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Nathan, Carl, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - N, Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Individuals, O-Z, Subseries 2
    - Oliver, Janet, 1977-1985 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Olmsted, Joanna, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Olsson, Bernard, 1981-1983 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - O, Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Parini, Isabelle Maridonneau, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Pearson, Carl M., 1971 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Persing, David, 1990-1994 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Peter, James B., 1989-1992 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Phillips, Paul E., 1977-1987 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Plotz, Charles M., 1971-1992 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Porter, Keith R., 1989 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous, P. (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous, Q. (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Rasmussen, Howard, 1984-1986 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Redlich, F.C., 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Relman, Arnold S., 1982-1985 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Reynolds, Charles F. III, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Rodnan, Gerald P., 1976-1983 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Rogers, David E., 1971-1986 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Root, Richard K., 1976-1985 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Roseff, Richard, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Rosenberg, Leon (Dean, Yale Medical School), 1984-1986 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Rosenthal, Ellen, 1988-1991 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Ross, Dennis W., 1981-1985 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Rothfield, Naomi, 1970-1978 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Ruddy, Shaun, 1977-1993 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - R, Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Sato, Hidemi, 1969-1994 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Schell-Frederick, Elizabeth W., 1973 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Schnitzer, Thomas J., 1974-1977 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Schoenborn, Florene, 1984-1986 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Schulman, Lawrence, 1982-1985 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Schwartz, William B., 1971-2002 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Scovern, Henry, 1979-1988 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Seegmiller, J. Edwin, 1966-1983 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Sergent, John S., 1989-1996 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Serhan, Charles, 1997-2007 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Simkin, Peter, 1977-1992 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Sinclair, David, 1981-1982 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Sipe, Jean D., 1986-1989 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Smallwood, Joan I. (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Smyth, Charley J., 1981-1993 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Spiera, Harry, 1978-1986 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Spilberg, Isaias, 1979-1992 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Steinman, Charles, 1969-1988 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Stern, Richard, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Stossel, Tom, 1974-1993 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - S, Miscellaneous 1/2 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - S, Miscellaneous 2/2 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Takasugi, Kiyoshi, 1989-1992 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Talbott, John H., 1974-1977 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Tan, Eng, 1970-1992 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Terino, Ellen, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Terkeltaub, Robert (Bob), 1991 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Thier, Samuel O., 1974-1984 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Thomas, Lewis, 1972-1983 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Thompson, George, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Tolone, Guiseppe, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - T, Miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - U, Miscellaneous (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Van Damme, Jo, 1987-2003 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      Van Damme collaborated with Malawista. See also Research Correspondence.
    - Volastro, Philip S., 1981-1983 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - V, Miscellaneous (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Wallace, Stanley, 1970-1990 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Ward, David, 1998-2000 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Weicker, Lowell P (Senator), 1986-1988 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Weiss, Mary, 1973-1976 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Weiss, Mary, 1977-1991 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Weissmann, Gerald, 1970-1990 (Box 9, Folder 10)
      Related Materials
      On Weismann, see also Box 12, Folder 15.
    - Weissmann, Gerald, 1991-2003 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Welt, Louis, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Wilson, Leslie, 1969-1974 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Winchester, Robert, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Wright, Daniel, 1983-1988 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - W, Miscellaneous (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Y, Miscellaneous (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Zabriskie, John B., 1985 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Zurier, Robert B., 1970-1992 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Zvaifler, Nathan J, 1968-1986 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Z, Miscellaneous, 1967-2002 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Unidentified correspondents, 1993 and no date (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Organizations, Subseries 3
    These files contain correspondence, membership lists, proposals sent to members, and other information about Malawista's participation in professional organizations and committees of these organizations. Organizations are arranged alphabetically. More information can be found in the Series 9, Talks and Travel.
    - American College of Physicians, 1969-1985 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      Malawista was elected a fellow of the American College of Physicians in 1970.
    - American College of Rheumatology (ACR), 1991 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Malawista served as President of ACR in 1991-1992. Folder includes records of several committee meetings Malawista attended. Annual meeting folders in Talks and Travel may contain additional information.
    - American College of Rheumatology (ACR), 1992, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - American College of Rheumatology, Planning Group, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      Malawista attended a meeting of the Planning Group of ACR in Key West, Florida on March 19, 1994 on the future of the College.
    - American Rheumatism Association (ARA), 1978, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      The American Rheumatism Association was a section of the Arthritis Foundation. Folders include information on committees on which Malawista served.
    - American Rheumatism Association (ARA), 1986-1988 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - American Rheumatism Association, International Affairs Committee, 1983-1984 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - ARA, Arthritis and Rheumatism, Editorial Board, 1976-1981, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 8)
      Arthritis and Rheumatism was the official journal of the American Rheumatism Association.
    - Arthritis Foundation, Fellowship Subcommittee, 1975-1977 (Box 10, Folder 9)
      Includes applications for fellowships to be considered by the committee.
    - Arthritis Foundation, Fellowship Subcommittee, 1977-1978 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Arthritis Foundation, Fellowship Subcommittee, 1978-1979 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Arthritis Foundation, Board of Trustees, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Arthritis Foundation, Board of Trustees, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Arthritis Foundation, "Research Advances", 1996-1998 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      Malawista was trying, with the help of others, to research and draft a detailed list of "research advances" in arthritis for the Arthritis Foundation. It is not clear whether the list was published.
    - Arthritis Foundation, Connecticut Chapter, Medical and Scientific Committee, 1969-1977 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Arthritis Foundation, Connecticut Chapter, Medical and Scientific Committee, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Arthritis Foundation, Connecticut Chapter, Medical and Scientific Committee, 1979 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Arthritis Foundation, Connecticut Chapter, Medical and Scientific Committee, 1980-1984 (Box 11, Folder 6)